There was a recent rules change to sagas
with the release of Secrets of
Strixhaven, and I thought this change
was a small nerve to sagas with read
ahead. But oh boy, was I wrong, and it's
so much worse than I thought. Not to
mention, I had a bunch of people tell me
that the rules have effectively changed
nothing, but that's not the case.
Let me explain. For some context, if you
haven't already, I highly recommend you
go and watch my previous video, linked
in the corner here.
Let's cover some things from that video.
First, a bunch of people were saying
that the main interaction I was talking
about, Doubling Season interacting with
sagas, has always worked that way, and
this new rule changes nothing.
For proof, I was cited the original
Dominaria mechanics article written by
Matt Tabak, a senior Magic editor and
the former Magic rules manager.
Where he says,
"In some unusual cases, you might add
more than one lore counter to a saga
simultaneously.
This can happen with effects like the
one on Doubling Season. If The Flame of
Keld enters the battlefield while you
control Doubling Season, it will enter
with two lore counters. This will cause
the chapter one and two abilities to
trigger, and you can actually put them
on the stack in either order." He does
then go on to say, and I think this is
important,
"The following turn, you'll add another
lore counter.
Note that Doubling Season won't affect
this turn-based action."
Matt Tabak also wrote the mechanics
article for the Final Fantasy set that
also happens to include Doubling Season
interacting with sagas.
"In some unusual cases, you may put more
than one lore counter on a saga at a
time. This can happen if you control a
permanent like Doubling Season." And
then there was the Brewer's Kitchen
video that featured sagas and Doubling
Season. And as you can see here,
Doubling Season doubles the amount of
token sagas, as well as having them
enter with two counters. So, was I wrong
here? Well,
not this time. In a thread on Blue Sky,
Matt does confirm that both the
Dominaria and Final Fantasy articles
were wrong, and that Doubling Season
wouldn't interact with sagas, but
because sagas entering with a counter
was not an effect, nor was the
turn-based action of adding a lore
counter.
He goes on to clarify that Inkeeper's
Talent or Vorinclex, Monstrous Raider
are cards that can interact with sagas
with the old rules. This is because
those cards specifically care about
counters being put on something, whereas
Doubling Season only interacted with
effects. So, what about Brewer's
Kitchen's video?
Well, I've done a video in the past
pointing out that Arena doesn't get all
of Magic's rules exactly right.
Now, before the Arena haters come out of
the woodwork, Arena gets the vast
majority of the rules of the game
correct. Otherwise, you'd see a whole
lot more videos from myself reporting on
the matter. Now, I wanted to clear up
one small thing I did get wrong in my
last video. So, to clarify, as of the
release of Secrets of Strixhaven, it is
no longer a straight rule that puts the
initial counters on sagas, it's an
intrinsic ability which creates a
replacement effect. Because of this
change, now Doubling Season will double
the amount of counters a saga enters
with.
Doubling Season will continue not to
interact with the turn-based action of
putting a counter on a saga you control
at the beginning of your first main
phase.
Now, the bit that I did get wrong was
with Read Ahead. In the video, I said
when you played a saga with Read Ahead
with Doubling Season in play, if you
picked anything more than the first
chapter, the saga would immediately end
and the chapters would all trigger.
That last part is incorrect. I was under
the impression that the choice you made
determined what chapters were skipped.
When in actual fact, all it comes down
to is the number of counters placed on
the saga.
So, if you decide you're going to read
ahead to chapter two with Doubling
Season in play, you'll go to put two
counters on the saga.
Doubling Season will see this and
replace that with four counters. The
saga enters with four counters and
because there's no chapter four, the
saga will be sacrificed as a state-based
action and nothing else will happen.
I want to clarify that this is specific
to sagas with Read Ahead. For normal
sagas and creature sagas, when they
enter with more than one counter or have
multiple counters placed on them, each
chapter will trigger once and then you
can stack them as you wish.
Rule 714.2b
covers this.
Was there anything else you think I
wasn't clear enough on and needed
explaining again? Perhaps you'd like me
to do a video on why you can't name
anything when you cast Meddling Mage
while there's a Humility in play. Let me
know in the comments. As always, if you
learned something, be sure to like this
video and subscribe because if you
don't, I'll get Wizards to change the
rules for sagas again next year. Thanks
for watching and I'll see you in the
next one.